<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gainefull cost. As it was delivered in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords, in the Abbey Church of Westminster, on VVednesday the 27. of November, being the day appointed for solemn and publike humiliation. By Henry Wilkinson, B.D. Pastor of Faiths under Pauls.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1610-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E23_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117193</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117193)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E23[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gainefull cost. As it was delivered in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords, in the Abbey Church of Westminster, on VVednesday the 27. of November, being the day appointed for solemn and publike humiliation. By Henry Wilkinson, B.D. Pastor of Faiths under Pauls.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1610-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Chr. Meredith and Sa. Gellibrand, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 1st, XXI, 24 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117193:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117193:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Gainefull Coſt. As it was delivered in A SERMON PREACHED Before the Right Honourable Houſe of LORDS, In the Abbey Church at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on Wedneſday the 27. of <hi>November,</hi> being the day appointed for ſolemn and publike Humiliation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Wilkinſon,</hi> B. D. Paſtor of <hi>Faiths</hi> under <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 CHRON. 31. 10. &amp;c.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since the people began to bring the offrings into the houſe of the Lord, we have had enough to eat, and have left plenty: for the Lord hath bleſſed his people; and that which is left, is this great ſtore.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>VERS. 21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>In every work that hee began in the ſervice of the houſe of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandements, to ſeek his God, he did it with all his heart, and proſpered.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for CHR. MEREDITH and SA. GELLIBRAND, dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117193:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117193:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Houſe of LORDS aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erſons of higheſt rank and eminent qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are</hi> ſatis amplum alter alteri thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum; <hi>but perſons ſo qualified, when they are employed in matters of greateſt and moſt publike concernment (as your Lordſhips are) become a</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſpectacle to the world, and to angels, and to men, 1 Cor. 4. 9. Look well how you behave your ſelves, for you now act either to the greateſt prejudice or profit of the Kingdome, and the Church of God. If the great wheel ſtands ſtill, the wheel within the wheel cannot move; and they had need move very cautiouſly, who if they move irregularly, prove fatall. Croſſe motions in the ſuperiour orbs of a State, doe as much trouble wiſe men to reconcile them to the principles of peace and government, as the Aſtronomers are troubled to ſave the Phoenomena, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning of Epicycles, and Concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricks, and Eccentricks: God forbid that any ſhould be put to the labour of coyning diſtinctions to ſalve the counter-paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or planetary motions in thoſe ſpheres in which the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt flarres of our State doe move.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was a pious as well as politick inſcription in the Court at</hi> Ratisbon, Quiſquis Senator curiam officii cauſa ingrede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ante hoc oſtium privatos affectus omnes abjicito: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camer. Cent. 1. c. 33.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:117193:3"/> iram, vim, odium, amicitiam, adulationem, Reip. perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, &amp; curam ſubjicito: nam ut aliis aequus, aut iniquus fueris, ita quoque Dei judicium expectabis aut ſuſtinebis. <hi>It is an inſcription not ſo fit to bee written on a Parliament houſe doore, as on every Parliament mans heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Lordſhips are not ignorant how much there is, not of weak man, but of wicked man in the great tranſactions of the Church and State. And I doubt not but you ſee and loath that generation (and there be many of them) who betake themſelves to a ſide meerly for hopes, intereſts, and engagements ſake; theſe are their</hi> ſumma credendorum &amp; agendorum, <hi>by theſe they act, and beleeve no further then theſe doe reach, theſe to them are the Law and Prophets. It is well enough known, that the interrogatory that</hi> Saul <hi>made to the Benjamites, is a moſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22. 7.</note> 
               <hi>concluding topick to mercenaries;</hi> Will the ſon of Jeſſe give every one of you fields and vineyards, and make you all Captaines of thouſands, and Captaines of hundreds? <hi>Theſe be they whoſe</hi> Cynoſura <hi>and poleſtar is profit, and the Kingdom their prey, and gold their god. We hope that your Lordſhips will take care, that ſuch as theſe are, ſhall never be great, and that great men ſhall never be ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall not trouble your Honours any further, nor will I in the leaſt kinde anticipate the book by giving ſo much as a taſte of the heads before hand; only thus much I could heartily wiſh, that as it is a Sermon of coſt, ſo it were a coſtly Sermon, every line of which were worthy to be written in letters of gold; the Authour would never think it too good to be thus dedicated ſince to be employed for your Lordſhips good, is the crown and happineſſe of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt devoted Servant in Chriſt, HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117193:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED before the Right Honourable Houſe of LORDS, At the publique Faſt <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. 1644.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 CHRON. 21. 24.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And King</hi> David <hi>ſaid to</hi> Ornan, <hi>Nay, but I will verily buy it for the full price: for I will not take that which is thine for the Lord, nor offer burnt offerings without coſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter you have <hi>David</hi> ſinning in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the people, v. 1, 2, 8. and begging pardon. Then you have the Lord puniſhing, verſ. 14, 15. after that, you have <hi>David</hi> and the Elders hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves before the Lord, verſ. 16. Now upon this great ſinne of <hi>David,</hi> and Gods great judgement upon that ſinne and <hi>Davids</hi> great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation upon that judgement, you have one of the greateſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and favours vouchſafed to <hi>David</hi> that his heart could wiſh; for you have a command given to <hi>David,</hi> to goe and ſet up an Altar in the threſhing Floore of <hi>Ornan</hi> the Iebuſite, v. 18. which place was afterward the place where <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple was built, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 3. 1. whereupon <hi>David</hi> did preſently ſet about the work, which was to prepare for the building of that Temple, chap. 22. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it pleaſeth God to order things, that great ſinnes being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, great judgements are inflicted, and great judgements pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce great humiliations, and great humiliations are great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the greateſt mercies. Our caſe is ſomewhat alike: we have ſinned grievouſly, God hath puniſhed us fearefully, we have hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117193:4"/> our ſelves, (I could wiſh I were able to ſay as <hi>David</hi> did) and I doubt not but the iſſue will bee, nay wee ſee it in ſome meaſure, the building the Lords houſe, of which <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple was but a Type.</p>
            <p>The words are a loving and noble anſwer, to a loving and noble offer; here is a pious contention betwixt two Kings (for <hi>Araunah</hi> was a King) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 3. who ſhould be at moſt coſt for God. <hi>Araunah</hi> thought that upon ſuch an occaſion, and at ſuch a time, he could not doe too much, and therefore he offers his threſhing Floor, and the Oxen for burnt offerings, and the threſhing inſtruments for wood, and the wheat for a meat offering, verſ. 23. but as <hi>Ornan</hi> thought he could not offer too much, ſo <hi>David</hi> thought he ſhould have offered too little if he had taken this, and as it were have paid his own debts to God upon another mans charges.</p>
            <p>We have two parts in the words: 1. <hi>Davids</hi> anſwer to <hi>Ornans</hi> offer: 2. <hi>Davids</hi> reaſon of that anſwer. In the firſt you have firſt the purchaſer, King <hi>David.</hi> Secondly the purchaſe he was to make. Thirdly the price in groſſe. Fourthly the fulneſſe of it. <hi>David</hi> doth not beat his bargaine, and bring it as low as he can, but is ready to give as much as the things were worth to the full.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>It becomes perſons of higheſt rank and quality, to offer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pend at the higheſt rate for God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond generall which is <hi>Davids</hi> reaſon, firſt obſerve his juſtice. It is thine, and I will not doe that injury unto thee, as to take thy goods upon thoſe termes: although <hi>Ornan</hi> offered freely upon <hi>Davids</hi> asking; yet <hi>David</hi> knew, that <hi>preces regum imperia ſunt;</hi> the deſires of Kings carry the force of commands. Secondly, his Piety: The thing he asked was for the Lord, now he thought it not becomming his piety to offer to God without expence.</p>
            <p>From his Iuſtice we collect this Doctrine: <hi>It is a piece of injuſtice to offer another mans goods, though it be to God himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly from his Piety we draw this Doctrine: <hi>A heart piouſly affected, will be expenſive and coſtly in the ſervice, and for the honour of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall handle only this laſt Doctrine, as being that which the Text holds forth moſt clearly. But before I come to the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, ſomething muſt be done by way of explication of the terms of the Doctrine: which ſhall be done by reſolving a queſtion or two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What doe wee meane by coſt? <hi>Resp.</hi> That eſpecially which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117193:4"/> concerns Temple work, or the building, and repairing, and advancing the Church of God, the houſe of Chriſt, which is ſo much out of repaire, ſo much run to ruine and decay. Then for the kindes of coſt that we would have men be at; they are, firſt, coſt and expence of time, which ought to bee redeemed, Eph. 5. 16. that it may be laid out for this work of God: we ſhould not meaſure out too narrow a ſcantling of time, eſpecially now in this juncture <hi>dum fervet opus;</hi> and therefore we ſhould purchaſe time from our ſleep, and recreations, and company, and meales, and eaſe, and lay it out upon this work that is now in hand. Secondly there is a coſt of labour, and paines, and diligence; we muſt make it our buiſineſſe, the travell of the heart, of the head, of the hand, they muſt all be laid out, in this work: wee muſt ſpend thus, and be ſpent; our ſtrength and parts which are the moſt coſtly things we have, they muſt goe all. Thirdly there is a coſt of ſubſtance when need requires; it muſt be good for quality, and large for quantity, if a man hath it. Fourthly there is a coſt of ſelfe, of life, when a man carries that in his hand as being ready to ſpend it in Gods ſervice, then a man is ſaid to lay out his life, when he adventures it, and puts himſelfe into danger of loſing of it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. when a man eſcapes unexpectedly a great danger, it is looked on as a ſacrifice even of the life, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 19. now that which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with danger and great difficulty, that hath coſt, as feares and teares, is fitteſt for God, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. 18. the ſword that <hi>David</hi> got with ſo much danger from <hi>Goliah,</hi> was fitteſt for God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it be asked what we meane by the ſervice of God? <hi>Reſp.</hi> This is taken either largely, for that whereby we ſerve the Lords provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our ſeverall places and callings. Or ſecondly it is taken in a more reſtrained ſenſe, for that which doth more immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Lord and his worſhip, and the building of his houſe. If perhaps I ſpeak of offering ſacrifices to the Lord in this buſineſſe, it is to be taken concerning ſacrifices in a morall not legall ſenſe. <note place="margin">The firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove the Doctrine, drawn from God. 1. In regard of the dignity of his perſon.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I now proceed to the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtrengthning the Doctrine. The firſt Argument to prove that a heart piouſly affected, will be expenſive in the ſervice and for the honour of God, is drawne from the object of this ſervice, God himſelfe. And in him we may conſider, firſt, the greatneſſe, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and majeſty of God: He is a great King, and therefore it is fit wee ſhould bee at coſt with him. The Lord doth expoſtulate in a chiding way, the matter betwixt himſelfe, and his people that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117193:5"/> to ſerve him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6. 8. He pleads his dignity, as if hee ſhould ſay, You pretend that I am your father and maſter; where is that reſpect and honour that theſe relations call for? will any of you dare to offer a baſe contemptible ſacrifice to your Governour? will he take it at your hands? what doe you make of me? am not I a great King and Governour? It was the ſaying of one, that as hee knew his owne diſtance, ſo he would have others know it too that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tabam mertibi tam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarem,</hi> Aug. Caeſ.</note> were inferiour to him; who, being invited to a feaſt by one of his ſubjects, but not finding ſuch entertainment as his dignity required, ſaid, hee did not know that he was ſo familiar with him till then. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> having ſpoken of the greatneſſe and dignity of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 15. then he tels verſ. 16. that <hi>Lebanon is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to burne, nor the beaſts thereof ſufficient for a burnt offering.</hi> Such is the greatneſſe of our God, that it is a derogation from his Majeſty, to offer any but the beſt unto him. Whence it is, that all thoſe that worſhip the Lamb, who is worthy, they therefore attribute all that ever they can to him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 11, 12, 13. ſo the wiſe men when they came to offer to Chriſt, they offered of the beſt the countreys afforded, for he was a King, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 2, 11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In regard of Gods commands: he calls for the beſt, <note place="margin">2. In reſpect of his commands.</note> and that which is beſt, is moſt coſtly. The equity of the Leviticall Lawes is yet in force: now the Lord did command the firſt fruits. <hi>Lev.</hi> 23. 10. and Exod. 34. 10. every firſtling that was male the Lord claimed that; of which we may ſay, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did of <hi>Reuben, Gen. 49. 3. Thou art my firſt-born, my might, and the begining of my ſtrength, the excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power:</hi> and <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. 19, 21. the males muſt be without blemiſh: and <hi>Levit.</hi> 22. 19, 20, 21, 22. the offering muſt be perfect; the pureſt oyle, the fineſt flowre, the fatteſt cattle were required: by all which was repreſented how that God would be ſerved with the beſt: he muſt have as the choiceſt of our ſubſtance, which is the moſt coſtly; ſo the choiceſt of our ſelves, of our ſtrength, and labours, and time, and whatſoever wee value beſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of Gods intereſt: He hath the greateſt intereſt <note place="margin">3. Becauſe of his Intereſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great.</note> in all we have, and therefore it is fit he ſhould have our coſt, our beſt, and all. Firſt, he hath intereſt by right of creation; whence it is that the 24 Elders uſe this as a reaſon of their doxology, <hi>Rev. 4. 11. Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, and honour, and power; for thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117193:5"/> Secondly, by right of purchaſe; and therefore the Apoſtle drawes his argument from this ground, <hi>That wee are bought by a price, and therefore we ought to glorifie God, &amp;c. 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 20. Thirdly, in regard of more then ordinary paines in our moſt coſtly and excellent things: our beſt ſervices come in a more ſpeciall manner from God: our beſt fruits come all from plants of his own ſetting and watering, and therefore, as the Apoſtle ſayes, 1 Cor. 9. 7. <hi>Who planted a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof?</hi> Hence it is that the Lord plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth againſt his people; upon this very ground he doth expoſtulate the matter, that he had been at much coſt and paines with them, and therefore it was great reaſon that they ſhould have made a return anſwerable ſome way to what hee had done, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 4. Fourthly, by an intereſt of Covenant: wee have bound our ſelves over to God, to give him the beſt, and hee hath bound himſelfe to give us the beſt; <hi>I will be thy God and you ſhall be my people,</hi> carries the beſt, and all that each other can doe: And therefore God layes it as one of the greateſt aggravations on his people, that they had failed in point of Covenant, <hi>Hoſ. 6. 7. They have tranſgreſſed the Covenant, there have they dealt treacherouſly:</hi> He ſayes, <hi>There,</hi> even where they ſhould have been moſt faithfull, even there have they proved Delinquents. Fifthly, by ſpeciall favours and obligations, this puts God into a further intereſt in our beſt ſervices; It is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own making, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 20, 21. to ſtirre them up to ſerve him, for <hi>he is thy prayſe, and he is thy God, that hath done for thee theſe great and terrible things, &amp;c.</hi> He uſeth the like argument, verſ. 12. 13, 14. to bring on the greateſt duty, verſ 19. Sixthly, by intereſt of conqueſt, he hath conquered our enemies, that had our beſt and moſt coſtly ſervices once, and hee hath freed us from them; and therefore it is fit hee ſhould have them now. It is the very preface to the whole Law, put in as an argument to Iſrael for obedience and beſt performances, in regard he had freed them from the bondage and vaſſalage of Aegypt: they ſerved the Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians with coſt and paines formerly, but now I have conquered them; therefore, let mee have your coſt and paines ſpent in my ſervice.</p>
            <p>2. A ſecond argument, to prove that wee ſhould be at coſt and paines in the ſervice of God, is drawn from the nature of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <note place="margin">The ſecond argument, is taken from the nature of the ſervice it ſelfe.</note> it ſelfe; Gods ſervice carries coſt in it: It engageth man in many difficulties and dangers: It will coſt a man his relations, his reputation, his intereſts, his ſubſtance, his life, his paines, and his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117193:6"/> and his deareſt ſelfe. Chriſt telling the very nature of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſayes that a man cannot be his Diſciple, unleſſe he denyes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 26, 27 and therefore verſ. 28. Our Lord Chriſt adviſeth men to conſider what his ſervice will coſt them, before they enter into it, and <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 23. He ſhewes that the coſt of his ſervice reacheth to ſelfe: It will coſt us labour and perhaps blood to, for it is a combate: it will coſt us ſweat, and moſt earneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, for it is a race, you muſt runne, and you muſt fight for it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 24, 25. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Herodolus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, will tell us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The greateſt ſervices require the greateſt paines and coſt; beſides, I may adde this, that Temple work, and the building the Lords Houſe, carries more then ordinary coſt; thoſe two books of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> will ſufficiently confirme this <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alcaeus</hi> hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s an alluſion to this purpuſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: danger and difficulty is in laying every ſtone of this building. The beſt things and the moſt excellent, doe carry with them, ever the greateſt coſt of paines, and travell, and ſubſtance: The very heathen gods in imitation of Gods ſervice, did expect the moſt coſtly ſervice, and what was <note n="c" place="margin">Hiero. Megi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerus. <hi>Arma Dio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ippi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orantia ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, fanum Grad. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an ma gis illa placent.</hi> Thom. Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totius. <hi>Sal Mars orna tur, ſpoliato ex i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ste, cruentis Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is, &amp; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is, caede ferc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s equi.</hi> The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of verſes <hi>in dona Templis conſecrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. omn. Hor.</hi>
               </note> offered to them, muſt be purchaſed at a deare rate, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 106. 37, 38. The Iſraelites ſerved Satan at a dearer rate, then they might have ſerved God.</p>
            <p>You have had the Doctrine confirmed; let us now ſee what is required in our offring, that ſo it may be accepted; for ſo it may fall out that a man may give a great deale, and yet bee at no coſt; and a man may give a very little, and yet be at a great deale of coſt: as appeares by thoſe that caſt in of their abundance into the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and the Widow that caſt in her mite only, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. And a man may take a great deale of paines to no purpoſe, and a man may be at leſſe paines ſometime to good purpoſe: Let us therefore ſee what ingredients muſt goe along with our ſervices to make them hold waight, and as will make them ſuch as God will own for coſtly ſervices; we ſee how the moſt coſtly and painefull ſervices have been <note place="margin">What ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to goe along with out ſervices to make them ſuch as will be accepted. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They muſt be without mixture,</note> refuſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 10, 11. 12. and a cup of cold water that carries no great expence of coſt or paines to give it, ſhall bee accepted; nay, the Lord expreſſely declares himſelf againſt Sacrifices of the greateſt expences, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. 7. Let us therefore examine what may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>required of thoſe that offer unto God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is required, that what wee offer to God, ſhould bee without mixture: It is a frequent complaint of the Lord againſt mixtures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 22. their wine mixed with water, and ſilver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come braſſe, and tynne was mingled with it: and the like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117193:6"/> wee have, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 18. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 18. By which expreſſions, was ſhewed how they were corrupted in their lives, by which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, the ſervice of God was ſowred in regard it mingled it ſelfe with it: It was alſo forbidden under the Law, that they ſhould plow with an Oxe and an Aſſe together, or weare linnen and wollen garments, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 10. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 19. Neither muſt they ſow their field with mingled ſeed. The Lord by there ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary actions did inſtruct them in his ſervice, how that hee would not have a mingled ſervice but a pure and holy worſhip, without mingling inventions of men, or our wayes and wills with Gods, though they ſeeme never ſo faire and plauſible. Swines blood was as good as Sheeps blood, and for colour there is no difference; yet the one was abhorred of God, and the other accepted: Now this pure ſervice of God is the moſt coſtly; as the fineſt flower, and the pureſt oyle without mixture of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne, or baſe ingredients; fine linnen without mixture of wollen, pure gold without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of droſſe, bright refined ſilver withut mixture of tynne, and ſimple wine without mixture of water, and the Oxe without the Aſſe; that is, the cleane without the uncleane, by all which the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are ſet forth, being things of the moſt value and greateſt price and coſt; to offer a ſervice to God free from our wills ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Gods, our pollutions mingled with his holy injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to offer him a ſervice free from our own hypocriſie; our own principles, our own leaven, to offer him a ſervice intirely his, with a totall ſelf-deniall, as it is a very difficult thing to fleſh and blood, nay impoſſible, ſo is it very coſtly in regard of the paines and ſweat, &amp;c. we muſt lay out in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that which we offer to God muſt be our own: But how <note place="margin">2 What wee give to God muſt bee our owne.</note> can that be? what ever we have is Gods already. I will not trouble you with diſtinctions of <hi>proprietas, &amp; jus, &amp; donum;</hi> but in brief, that we have may be ſaid to be ours and Gods too, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 3. <hi>David</hi> ſayes, he had prepared of his own proper coſt, and yet ver. 14. 16. it was ſaid to be Gods <note n="a" place="margin">1 What <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mius</hi> ſayes concerning <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera bona,</hi> may be applyed to our purpoſe, ſpeaking how they can be ſaid to be <hi>noſtra. Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>untur</hi> noſtra, <hi>quia à Deo donata nobis, neque quaerentibus, neque prome, entibas:</hi> for which hee qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, Tract. 30. Tom. 5. Noſirum enim quod nobis dotur ab alio, ergo &amp; illud quod nobis denatur à Deo: Sic Chriſtus noſter eſt. 2. Opera</hi> noſtra <hi>dicuntu contradiſtinctè alienis. 3. Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tura aliquando uſcribit gratiam &amp; gloriam nobis, aliquando Deo: ut</hi> Paulus <hi>vult nos</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſalutem noſtram, nos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere, &amp;c. Interdum aſcribit Deo utramque, Deum dare velle &amp; perficere,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame may be ſaid of that we offer to God; ſometimes it is called <hi>ours,</hi> ſometimes it is called <hi>Gods.</hi> Dub. Evangel. <hi>c. An. &amp; quomodo bona opera noſtra?</hi>
               </note>: Therefore when I ſay ourown, I meane
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117193:7"/> not only in reſpect of ſome propriety and intereſt by the Civill lawes of a State, for all the things, and their very title by which the wicked doe poſſeſſe them, are impure <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15. but their owne in reſpect of a higher title, and better intereſt as holding all <hi>in captie</hi> in and by Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22, 23. he that builds a Church by that which he hath gotten by uſury or bribery or by falſe dealing which he hath exerciſed againſt the Saints, he raiſeth a materiall temple upon the ruines and bones of the ſpirituall temples. He that gives to the poore that which he gets from others injuriouſly, he ſerves God upon other mens charges. He that performs any ſpirituall duty there muſt be the actuall exerciſe of a mans own gifts, or elſe it is not accepted. For, ſuppoſe one joyne in prayer with another, and heares a ſermon, if a mans owne faith &amp;c. be not engaged in the buſineſſe, though they bee excellently performed in regard of him with whom he joynes; yet this is to offer a ſervice which is not ones owne: no man muſt ſpend for God at another mans coſt, or be at another mans finding, every one muſt ſerve him in the ſweat of his owne brows. He that gives that to God which he takes from others, this is theevery rather then bounty. We may ſpeak of mens offering to God, as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Teſtari ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uut impubes, religiouſus Filius in ſacris, morti damnatus, &amp; obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Crimine damnatus, cum muto ſurdus, &amp; ille Qui Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtatem l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſit, ſit caecus &amp; ipſe.</hi> Vid. Io. ab Imol. in c. <hi>qua Ingredientibus de teſta. extra.</hi> In every one of thoſe there is ſome deſect, ſome want; either he is not <hi>ſui juris,</hi> or he wants his ſenſes, &amp;c. <hi>Vid. H. Swinburne B. of Civill Law, 2 part of briefe Treat. of Teſtaments and Wills.</hi> 3 What we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, muſt bee free and with a willing mind.</note> Civilians doe concerning thoſe that they ſay may not bequeath or give away by teſtament; if they be not their own men, or at their owne diſpoſing, or the like, they cannot give.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that which we offer to God, we muſt offer freely without conſtraint, of a ready minde and willingly; we muſt offer our hearts in the ſacrifice we give, and ſervice we perform to God. The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilians have a diſtinction betwixt <note n="b" place="margin">Munus <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè eſt, quod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariò obimus lege, more, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve ejus, qui jubendi habet poteſtatem.</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>autem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè ſunt, quae nulla neceſſitate juris, of ſicii, ſed ſponte praeſtantur, quae ſi non praeſtentur, reprehenſio eſt: &amp; ſi praeſtentur, plerumque law ineſt.</hi> Pancirol. de Donis, and he out of <hi>Marcian. l. Manus, de verb. ſignif.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>donum</hi> and <hi>munus:</hi> that is <hi>munus</hi> which is performed upon duty, that is <hi>donum</hi> which a man may chuſe whether he will doe or offer or no, as being free in the thing. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we offer to God, we are bound to doe it, and ſo in their ſenſe it cannot be <hi>donum</hi> but <hi>munus:</hi> however, if it be with the heart, we may ſay in a theologicall ſenſe, that it is a freewill offering; when we offer our hearts, wills, and affections, we offer freely; and then we are ſaid to give to God. That man that doth not offer his heart,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117193:7"/> though perhaps he may doe much, and give much, as they did, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. &amp;c. yet their ſervice is not looked on as a coſtly ſervice, it wants the heart. But he that offers never ſo little, yet if he gives the heart, he offers coſt, he gives himſelfe, it is worth a whole world. He gives freely that gives all, though he gives never ſo little; and he gives as much as any can doe, for he leaves himſelfe nothing, that gives himſelfe in the gift. This is the coſt God looks at more then all the treaſures in the world. And therefore <hi>David</hi> in that great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe of preparing for the Temple, exhorts the Princes of Iſrael to ſet their hearts and their ſouls to ſeek the Lord 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 19. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> therefore and build,</hi> &amp;c. by which he ſhowes clearly, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the heart were in the buſineſſe, it would be nothing worth. So when the Tabernacle was to be ſet up, there was proclamation made, that whoſoever was of a willing minde ſhould bring his offering, &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 2. ſo alſo it is obſerved, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35. 21. how willingly they came and offered their hearts: it is noted likewiſe ver. 22. and 29. how freely they gave: and <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. 5, 6. it is obſerved that they were ſo hearty in the work, that there was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſtraint laid upon them that they ſhould give no more. In 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 2. it is ſaid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that he prepared with all his might for the houſe of God: and ver. 3. hee ſet his affection to the work, whence followed his coſt, ver. 9. there was great rejoycing, not at the offering, but the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling offering, and that it was with a perfect heart, ver. 9. repeated againe ver. 14. with thanks for a willing heart, and ſpoken of with humble acknowledgment, ver. 17. whence we may learne, that it is the heart that makes the ſacrifice and ſervice a coſtly one to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and that which is accepted of the Lord. He ſerves God at an an eaſe and a cheap rate, and indeed he offers ſleight ſtuffe to the Lord, which offers a heartleſſe, negligent, careleſſe ſervice.</p>
            <p>4. What we offer to God, it muſt be offered wholly to him: <note place="margin">4. It muſt bee offered to God alone, without ſharing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and any other.</note> as it muſt be <hi>integrè</hi> in reſpect of the heart, ſo it muſt be <hi>integrum</hi> in reſpect of God. We muſt not joyne any other with the Lord in our offering; for, if we come to divide in our ſervices, though they be never ſo coſtly, yet God hath no ſhare at all, if he hath not all. he that puts his own Intereſts, or names his own ends with Gods, offers nothing to God, but all to himſelfe. He that thus divides, makes ſure of all; for God, having right to all (as the true mother of the childe. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 26.) will not endure a ſharing and parting of his own peculiar. A divided offering betwixt God and our ſelves, or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117193:8"/> ſins, or the world, or men, is not a coſtly one to God, for it is none at all. The Phariſees did give almes, and faſt, and pray &amp;c. to be ſeen of men, though they were ſervices pretended to be offered to God, and ſuch as coſt them paines and money; yet they offered that which coſt them nought to God. A man builds an Hoſpitall, or Temple, or the like, at very great expences; yet if his own name and honour be inſcribed on the work; if a mans own honour be twiſted with Gods glory, this is not to offer coſt to God, but to a mans own ſelfe. He that gives to God, with reſpect to himſelfe, he doth not ſo much give or offer a gift, as drive a bargaine; he offers to himſelfe and not to God.</p>
            <p>5 There be ſome ſpeciall ingredients which are required in him <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſon moſt bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that offers. 1. He that offers any thing to God, muſt doe it in faith, without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. It is ſaid alſo, <hi>That by faith Abel offered a more excellent ſacrifice then Cain,</hi> v. 4. It may be <hi>Cain</hi> might offer as good for ſubſtance as his brother did, but faith put an excellencie into it: or, if this be not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then we may underſtand it thus, That by faith <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bel</hi> took more paines then <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſought out the beſt he had to offer to God, whereas <hi>Cain</hi> took that which came next to hand. Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives all from God, and offers all to God againe; it ſticks at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Abraham</hi> had rather (I doubt not) have offered his whole eſtate then his ſonne; but Faith offers him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 17. by Faith the godly offered themſelves to the greateſt tortures in the world, verſ. 35, 36, 37. and he that offers up himſelfe to God, to be a holy, and a lively, and an acceptable ſacrifice, he offers the greateſt and moſt coſtly ſacrifice that he can doe.</p>
            <p>2. Love is a ſecond ingredient: this is a coſtly grace. It was Gods love that made him ſo expenſive towards us: <hi>God ſo loved the world, Iohn 3 16. that he gave his only begotten Son,</hi> &amp;c. according as a man loves, ſo he ſpends, He that loves his ſports, ſpends his eſtate on them: we are moſt coſtly on that vanity that we love. Love will be at labour and coſt. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerved a hard apprentiſhip, but Love ſweetned it ſo, that-the time ſeemed but a few dayes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. 18, 19, 20. Love is even prodigall, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>Mary took a pound of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yntment very coſtly,</hi> and ſpent it on Chriſt, though <hi>Iudas</hi> could ſay, <hi>Why is all this waſte?</hi> yet ſhe (I doubt not) would be as ready to ſay, Oh that I had more! I can never doe too much for Chriſt. Love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very laborious and ſedulous as well as expenſive. Men, we ſee, take
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117193:8"/> any paines for gaine, and that which makes the wheels run merrily is the oyle of love: This the Apoſtle takes notice of, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 3. the work of faith, and labour of love.</p>
            <p>3. Zeale is required in our coſt; and that coſts very little that <note place="margin">3. Zeale.</note> doth not coſt us zeale: this will lay out what a man hath, and what a man is, his ſubſtance and himſelfe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 9. and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 17. wee may ſee how <hi>David</hi> the type, and Chriſt the Antitype were eaten up by zeale of Gods houſe; this is it which heightens the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that drawes out all the treaſures of the ſoule, that tranſports the affections, and ſets an edge on them, and is like <hi>Elijahs</hi> fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, in which the ſoule rides, and is carried in the ſervice of God. The zeale of the affections is the expence of them, they are ſet on broach by zeale, and they will all run out and be exhauſted for God. Zeale is the flames of the ſoule, which waſtes and conſumes all in the ſoule for God: it puts a note and ſtamp of eminencie and ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity on every thing. Love, if zealous, is ſtrong as death; it is a tranſportment and raviſhment, that is the high note of it. Thy faith, if edged with zeale, riſeth up with confidence and full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: Thy ſelfe-denyall, if zealous, is a kind of ſelfe-cruelty; thou wilt out with thy luſtfull eyes, and off with thy offending hands: Thy patience, if zealous, is hardneſſe and long-ſuffering, and great ſuffering, and extream ſuffering, and all ſuffering. The riches of the heart lye in Zeale, and are laid out by Zeale. It is the ſtrength of the ſoule. As it was ſaid of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that his ſtrength did lye in <note place="margin">4. Prudence, <hi>Nota<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dignunt eſt, Deum volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, &amp; oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſale condi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, &amp; mandato ter repetito, Lov. 2. 13, ut deſignare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſymbolice omne ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; ſapientiae &amp; prudentiae, &amp; ſale int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gritatu, incorruptionis &amp; innocentiae condo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rid. Sphano. Dub. Evang. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> his haire, and when that was cut off, he was as an ordinary man: ſo I may ſay of zeale, the ſtrength lyes there; take away that, and a man becomes an ordinary man: There cannot be a coſtly ſacrifice without the fire of Zeale.</p>
            <p>4. Prudence is required: It is the ſacrifice of a foole without prudence. Under the Law there was a ſpeciall command, that every ſacrifice ſhould be ſeaſoned with ſalt, which is the * ſymbole of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; what we offer to God muſt coſt us the expence &amp; travell of the brain, as well as the ſweat of our browes and the beſt of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. We muſt caſt about and contrive the beſt way wee can to lay out our ſelvs in that we offer to God. Chriſt puts us upon that courſe by ſhewing us how that men if they be to undertake any great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will firſt ſit down and conſider, and wiſely fore-caſt with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what way and by what meanes they may bring about their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. <hi>Luc.</hi> 14. 28. 31. He that is not a good husband for the Lord,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117193:9"/> and a wiſe Steward in improving things for the beſt advantage for God, he may loſe all his coſt, and therefore there muſt be a coſt of wiſdome in what we offer to the Lord.</p>
            <p>5. It muſt be offered by the hand of a Mediatour whatever we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to God. He that offers the beſt ſacrifice in the world to God, <note place="margin">5. What is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered muſt be given up by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Mediator.</note> but doth not offer it by the hands of Chriſt, offers a ſacrifice of no worth: wherefore in the Law anciently it was commanded, that though the ſacrifice were a male and without blemiſh, ſo that there could be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o exception againſt the ſacrifice; yet it was to be brought to the Prieſt and to be offered by his hands. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev.</hi> 17. 3, 4. &amp;c. The Prieſt was to ſtay it and to offer it; it was death to do otherwiſe. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner now it is: Suppoſe a man prays, or heares, &amp;c. and he doth it in the moſt exact manner; yet if he preſents theſe ſervices in his own name and not in the name of Chriſt, if he doth not bring his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Prieſt the Lord Chriſt, if he doth not bring his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Prieſt the Lord Chriſt, and that he offers it in his name, it will be loathed. It is not becauſe we perform a duty in the moſt excellent manner that it is accepted, but becauſe Chriſt our High-Prieſt preſents both us and our ſervices to the Lord: So that if a man ſhould offer as many ſacrifices as were at the Dedication of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omons</hi> Temple and all without blemiſh, and that the perſons were clean that offer them, and that all qualifications did meet that are required; yet all theſe are accurſed, if they be offered in their owne name: the leaſt things that were offered, even an Epha, or a Gomer, or a payre of Turtle Doves, or a mite, were accepted from the hand of the Prieſt, when rivers of Oyle ſhould be refuſed, if preſented o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. This is ſet out in the type, <hi>Levit.</hi> 5. 8. <hi>ad</hi> 11. every ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice muſt be ſprinkled with Chriſts blood, this is the chiefe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient; his incenſe muſt go along with the ſacrifice, and then he will ſmell a ſweet ſmelling favour, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. 11. &amp; 16. 11, 12 13. All our performances muſt be dipped in his blood, and be preſented by his hands, and then the Lord will accept them; for in him alone he is well pleaſed: thoſe ſervices are coſtly indeed that are beſprinkled with Chriſts blood, and offered up by Chriſts hands.</p>
            <p>Having confirmed the Doctrine, and ſhewed how we muſt <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the practice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doctrine confirmed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out for God layes up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſay out our coſt for God, I proceed in the next place to propoſe ſome Conſiderations to move you to the practice of the dutie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He that layes out his coſt for God, eſpecially in Temple-work, layes up a treaſure for himſelfe; he lends to the Lord, and he will be his pay-maſter. If any thing in the world can put God in debt to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117193:9"/> creature; this will; he is pleaſed to enter bond (as it were) for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all arreares in this kinde. So it pleaſed God to order things, that though there was a whole tribe taken out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the children of Iſrael to ſerve at the Sanctuary; yet when they came to be reckoned the ſecond yeare, and the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> was left out, it is found that the number is juſt the ſame to a man as it was before that tribe was taken away, as appeares by <hi>Exod.</hi> 38. 26. &amp; <hi>Num.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 46. the ſumme in both, ſix hundred thouſand, three thouſand five hundred and fifty men; So that there were ſo many young men of 19. yeares old as now ſupplyed the want of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites which were ſet apart for Gods ſervice, that the people of God might ſee that they ſhould be no loſers, though they gave a whole Tribe to God. There is a bleſſing promiſed to them that ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Temple-work. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 18. 19. And how were <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> and <hi>Ezrah,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> bleſſed in the work? How was <hi>Hezekiah</hi> bleſſed, and all the people alſo, with abundance, after they brought offerings to the houſe of the Lord? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 10. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord takes ſpeciall notice of all thoſe that doe engage <note place="margin">2. The Lord takes exact notice of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and their behaviour in this buſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that he may accordingly reward them.</note> themſelves in this Temple work; he takes notice of all particulars, that he may be ſure to reward men accordingly. 1. He obſerves if a man have but a diſpoſition to a good work; he lookes into pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of a mans ſoule; they ſtand not for cyphers before him, but carry great weight with them, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8. 10. How well did God take the very purpoſes of <hi>David</hi> in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe? 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. 8. 2. He takes notice of the time punctually when men doe ſet about his work, he puts down the day of the month in the Almanack of Heaven, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 18. and this is onely that he might bleſſe them from that day forward. 3. He takes notice of what men doe give to his work, to aſhekel, <hi>Num.</hi> 7. So alſo 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 6, 7, 8. is ſet down what the Princes offered; likewiſe <hi>Ezra</hi> 2. 68, 69. there is ſet down to a dram of gold, and the pounds of ſilver which were offered: he hath his book of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, in which he ſets down exactly the gifts to Temple-work, that he might require them to a dram, and to a ſhekel; nay, that he might pay uſe for what they ſo lend. What an honour is it that the contribution-money, and the names of thoſe that gave, ſhould ſtand upon record to all poſterity? 4. He takes ſpeciall notice of the willingneſſe of mens hearts in his work, and therefore it is often ſet down, how willingly every one offered to the Tabernacle, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117193:10"/> to the Temple, Exod. 25. 2. &amp; 35. 21, 22, 29. 1 Chron. 29. 9. their willingneſſe twice obſerved there, and v. 14. taken notice of again; v. 17. twice more ſpoke of; the Lord looks on this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he requites men according to this, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12. If there were any that did offer unwillingly amongſt them before cited, they are not taken notice of, as being unworthy the very naming. 5. The Lord take notice of mens carriage and behaviour in the buſineſſe, how they doe advance his work or hinder it in any kind, that ſo he may deal with them accordingly; he obſerves what paines, as well as what coſt men are at, <hi>Neh.</hi> 3. how they did carry on the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Temple: what part ſuch a one built, and what part ſuch a one; what proportion and meaſure they had, how farre they went: It is noted of ſome of the builders, how they repayred, and laid the beames, and ſet up the doores, and the locks, and the barres, ver. 3, 6, 13, 14, 15. the Lord takes notice even to a barre, a beam and and lock; he obſerves further, how they went thorow with the work, it did not ſtick on their hands; he obſerves of one, how he and his daughters did ingage themſelves, v. 12. the weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of this ſex ſhall not be omitted, v. 5. there is a note of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny ſet upon the nobles of the Tekoites, and others, that either did withdraw from the work, or hinder it from going forward. <hi>Neh.</hi> 3. 5. it is ſaid the Tekoites repaired, but the Nobles would not put their necks to the work, the Nobles ſtigmatized; then, chap. 4. 1, 2, 3, 8, 11. you have the reproaches and affronts ſet down which the enemies did offer to them that were in the work: Vpon that you have ſet down the valour, courage, and reſolution of thoſe that did fall to the work maugre all oppoſitions whatſoever, v. 16, 17, &amp;c. then ch. 6. you have a treaty propounded, but not yeelded to, v. 10. &amp;c. they would have drawn him perhaps to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; but <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> as he will not ſend to the adverſaries, ſo neither will have to doe with them when they ſend to him: Then you have ſet down what intercourſe of Letters there were betwixt the Nobles of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> and how there was an oath paſſed from them to him, in regard he was a great man, v. 17, 18. It is ſet down alſo how theſe treachetous Nobles did extoll <hi>Tobiah</hi> to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and told <hi>Tobiah</hi> what ever he ſaid of him; upon which <hi>Tohiah</hi> ſent him Letters to make him afraid. The Nobles of the Tekoites, and the Nobles of <hi>Iudah</hi> have a very ill name in this whole work. Hence we may obſerve, that God takes ſpeciall notice
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117193:10"/> of underminers and oppoſers of the work, and ſets a black coale upon them, that in due time he may remember them according to their deeds. Wherefore, ſince God doth obſerve every mans carriage ſo exactly as he doth in that work, which doth more immediatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern his own glory, every one had need be the more carefull to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves faithfull and diligent in that work, and to offer themſelves moſt willingly in that ſervice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A third argument, to offer to God all our labours, and <note place="margin">3. An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the builders of Babel.</note> to be at coſt in his ſervice, may be drawn from thoſe that are at ſo much paines and coſt in the building of Babel, and in oppoſing the building of the Lords houſe; they move every ſtone, they leave nothing unattempted, whereby they may retard, or put back, or obſtruct any way that building. It coſts them not only a great deale of paines and vexation of ſpirit, and vaſt expences, but the loſſe of their ſoules to boot. Let us but look on the Antichriſtian par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Kingdome, and ſee how induſtrious they are, how vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, how wiſe in their generation to make uſe of all advantages to promote their deſignes; they doe not offer to the Divell that which coſts them nought: hee is a hard Maſter, and his ſervice is a very troubleſome, dangerous, deſperate ſervice, and yet how zealous are they in it? How many lifes have been ſacrificed in it? Let it never bee ſaid, that Satan ſhould have more coſt beſtowed on him, more paines, and care, and time laid out in his drudgery, then the noble, and honourable, and glorious work of God, now in your hands, ſhould have beſtowed on it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The excellency of the ſervice, together with the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, ſhould be a great incentive to the work, to draw out your <note place="margin">4. From the excellency of the work: this reſpects noble ſpirits in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner.</note> coſt, and lay out your paines in it. This to a noble ſpirit is one of the greateſt perſwaſives; which to a low, degenerous, poore ſpirit, is a diſcouragement. If it be matter that carries weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance in it, and that it is
<q>—<hi>dignus vindice nodus,</hi>
               </q> who ſo fit to undertake it as one of <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies? Now there is ſomething in noble perſons, truly noble, which as it is an incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, ſo likewiſe it is an engagement on their ſpirits, that they of all men ſhould undertake the moſt difficult ſervice, and the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, which is the building the Lords Houſe. It is ſaid concerning water that comes from Springs and Fountaines, that it will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend and riſe in a Conduit or Ciſteme ſo high as the head of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117193:11"/> Spring lies, but no higher: ſo it is with the ſpirits of men, thoſe that are of a low baſe deſcent will not riſe up to any high employments; but thoſe that are of a high deſcent riſe up without forcing or conſtraint to the higheſt enterpriſes: Hence it was, that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roes did deſire to be accounted of the off-ſpring of the gods, and men did deſire to perſwade great perſons that they were ſo deſcended, that ſo their ſpirits might be raiſed up to their ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: <note n="a" place="margin">In <hi>Lucian</hi> we have him thus ſpeaking, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. And <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſayes thus, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ut ſe &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fortes, eitam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> falſam ſit, ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> genito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> credant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to moilo an mus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lut elivina <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fiducians ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, res magnas aggred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eda: pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> us, agat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> earitate ſaeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> thought it very conducible to him that he was eſteemed the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> for he was feared by reaſon of this opinion men had of him, by the Heathens. We ſhall finde the Ancients very ambitious in this kind; ſo the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaid they were deſcended of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus; Hercules</hi> and <hi>Perſens</hi> are reported to ſpring from <hi>Iupiter; Seleucus</hi> of <hi>Apollo; Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> of a Dragon: and the maine reaſon was, that they might have a greater engagement on their ſpirits to doe nobly: Whence alſo it was, that men of low parts, and ſuch as would not or could not undertake great matters, were called <hi>terrae filii.</hi> So that it is cleare, that noble ſpirits have great engagements on them for the undertaking of great deſignes: It lies more upon them then upon other men, they ſeeme to degenerate, when they begin to feare or draw back.</p>
            <p>A truly generous and noble ſpirit is ſo far from being diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by difficulties, that, like the Palm, the more weight it hath laid upon it, it gathers ſtrength the more to encounter the Aſſaylant: Hence it is, that thoſe that ſtood before the Throne had palmes in their hands, the enſigne of victory. You have a remarkable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſuch a ſpirit as wee ſpeak of in <hi>Caleb, Numb.</hi> 13. when the Spies had ſeen the Anakims and Gyants, the walled Cities, and thoſe multitudes of enemies, verſ. 28. 29. their hearts began to faint; but <hi>Calebs</hi> ſpirit did riſe at them, and he ſaid, <hi>Let us goe up at once, and poſſeſſe it, for we able,</hi> ver. 30. but the others hearts failed them. ver. 31. So againe, when theſe white-liver'd Spies did diſcourage others by their feare, <hi>Caleb</hi> ſhewes his courage, chap. 14. 9. and ſayes, <hi>They are bread for us:</hi> It is ſaid of him, he was a man of another ſpirit, ver. 24. It was valiantly reſolved by <hi>Agis</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Apud Manti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> adverſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> plures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg</note>, when he was diſſwaded from going againſt his enemies, becauſe they were more in number, he ſaid, <hi>He that will conquer many muſt encounter many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this may further appear to your Lordſhips, give me leave to confirm this fourth inducement to the great work of God by ſome ſpeciall argument reſpecting the condition of your perſons:</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117193:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, it hath pleaſed God to place you as ſtarres of a greater mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude in a ſuperiour Orbe; now it is certain, that by your light <note place="margin">Arguments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndition of Nobles and your Lordſhips in a ſpeciall manner.</note> and influences, which you may diffuſe farther then others, you may doe much more then others can do in any great buſineſſe: for to whom the Lord hath given ſuch eminent talents, who is ſo fit to conquer the greateſt difficulties as they are? theſe are the Chariots and horſemen of a State. if theſe do not undertake great things, who ſhould? God looks for more to whom he hath given more: If thoſe that are the vitalls of a body politick do not undertake the weightieſt buſineſſes; how can it be expected, that thoſe that live in a manner upon their influences ſhould: When the Lord hath any dangerous ſervice and difficult, who is ſo fit to ſay, here am I, ſend me as a <hi>Jeremy, Jer.</hi> 6. 8. doth not the cauſe of Chriſt ſay now, who is on my ſide, who? Is it not now ſaid, who will defend me now, I am bleeding and ſinking? Who ſo fit as Nobles, and honourable perſons, they are fitteſt to engage for a noble and honourable Cauſe? who ſo fit to deale with difficulties like Goliahs and Anakims, as our <hi>Sampſons, Joſhuahs, Davids, Calebs, Nehemiahs, Zerubbabels,</hi> men of excellent and noble ſpirits. Every qualification is a particular engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſtrongly binds you to the greateſt ſervices; the greater Wheels and ſuperiour Orbs muſt move others. Wherefore, as the Elders ſpeaking to <hi>Boaz,</hi> prayed that his wife might be like <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> and like <hi>Leah, which two did build the houſe of Iſrael;</hi> and to him they ſaid, <hi>do thou worthily in Ephratah, and be famous in Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem, Ruth</hi> 4. 11. The ſame I wiſh of your Lordſhips, that you may build the Houſe of God and do famouſly in England, and as thoſe Nobles did we read of <hi>Num.</hi> 21. 18. make uſe of their ſtaves, which ſome think were Enſigns of honour, to digge a well for the publike good; ſo I wiſh that you would make that uſe of your honours for publike ſervice, which as they are gliſtering, to make you more conſpicuous then others, ſo are they binding to make you more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As noble perſons have greater advantages in regard of qualifications, ſo they have greater advantages then others in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the opportunities preſented to them, to carry on the moſt difficult ſervices: cauſes and perſons become humble ſuiters to men in great place, and expect ſhelter and protection from their wings, opportunities are candidates, and become petitioners to them.</p>
            <p>Who hath ſo great an advantage to diſcover dangers at a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117193:12"/> diſtance, as thoſe that like <hi>Saul</hi> are taller by the head and ſhoulders then other men? Or thoſe that are placed in the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towers of a State: Who hath opportunity to doe more, then thoſe that when they move, doe move whole legions at once? you are as the Magazines and Treaſures of the State you have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to furniſh out thouſands, with amunition and artillery for ſervice: by how much the more that others doe depend upon ſuperiours, by ſo much the more opportunity they have of doing good: you ſtand upon the vantage ground in regard of others, and by that meanes you may the more promote and carry on the cauſe of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The eyes of God and man are upon you, and upon eminent perſons more then on others: It is expected that you ſhould be the <hi>Primipili,</hi> the <hi>Anteſignani,</hi> the firſt to ſet upon dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties: men look at you that they may write after your copies; your actions being written in capitall letters; men uſually make ſuch as you are, their levell, and <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayes, concerning private men, that their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues have tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unhappineſſe that <hi>priuſquam apparent diu luctantur,</hi> yet they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced in this <hi>quod &amp; vitia tendras habent,</hi> but hee ſayes more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>nullius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis cavend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> qualem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quam qui qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemcunque ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urint mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> de Clem.</note> ayme, and ſquare, and rule. A godly noble man is, <hi>norma publica,</hi> he is as a publike ſtandard, men walk by his rule, and meaſure themſelves by his line: If a publike perſon failes, he murthers the expectations and hopes of thouſands at once <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ad rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ad ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudmem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Sen.</note>; juſt as you doe, others will doe the like, you ſee when <hi>Abimelech</hi> cut down a bough and laid it on his ſhoulder, all the people did the like, <hi>Iud.</hi> 9. 48, 49. God Almighty expects more from you, and from ſuch as are of eminent parts; for as he hath drawn ſome fairer characters and prints of his own image with his finger in their ſoules; ſo he expects they ſhould hold them forth that others might copy out their excellencies; beſides, God hath been at greater coſt and charges with you, he hath maintained you at a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate, he hath laid out much of the treaſures of his goodneſſe, and hath ſpent upon you a great deale of the riches of his bounty on you; and therefore hee doth expect, and will require a greater account from you, then from men of an inferiour rank; to whom much is given, much will be required, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 48.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Then a fourth argument, may be taken from the ſucceſſe that you are like to find in carrying on this work. Doe but ſee what an encouragement <hi>David</hi> had, ſo farre as hee went in this work, how did the Lord proſper him, and what exceeding great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion did he lay in for the work, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 2, 3. &amp;c. then ſee how the Lord encouraged <hi>Solomon,</hi> verſ. 13. and how did the work goe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117193:12"/> on and proſper in his hands. Againe, conſider how God did engage himſelfe to thoſe that did rebuild the Temple, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 44. 28. &amp; 45. 1. 2, 3, 13, 14. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 4, 5, 8. The Lord that has the diſpoſing of power and riches, and all things in his hands, promiſeth that they ſhall be ſubſervient to that great work, to which alſo, wee adde <hi>Zech.</hi> 4. 5, 6. where the Lord engageth himſelfe in a ſpeciall manner, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and carry on that work, in a wonderfull and extraordinary way: Whence I argue, that if the Lord was ſo gracious as to promiſe, and to performe his word to them that were engaged in his work antiently, them ſurely, hee will doe it now; if to them that were employed in building the materiall Temple, much more to them that ſhall lay out themſelves in building the myſticall Houſe of God, by how much the more this doth excell the Type? There might be ſet down many other encouragements, but I forbeare in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I have done it in another diſcourſe before the other honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe.</p>
            <p>I come now to make fome uſe of this, and to apply to our ſelves. <note place="margin">Vſe, firſt of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts of people.</note> There be divers ſorts of people to be reproved. Firſt, thoſe that are very ſurly and churliſh towards Chriſt and his work: if you come to them, and deſire their aſſiſtance and furtherance in the cauſe of Chriſt; they, like as <hi>Nabal</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> give a very dogged an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 1 <hi>Sam. 25. David</hi> ſent to him in his diſtreſſe for ſome reliefe, <hi>and he anſwered Davids ſervants, and ſaid, Who is David? and who is the ſon of Ieſſe?</hi> and ver. 11. <hi>Shall I take my bread, and my water, and my fleſh that I have killed for my ſhearers, and give it unto whom I know not whence they be?</hi> Juſt ſuch an anſwer you have from many, they will ſay, they muſt maintaine their families, they have wifes and children, and they cannot ſpare what they have provided for them to give to they know not whom: they may well ſay, for they know not whom, for Chriſt is unknown to them: They are of <hi>Judas</hi> his minde, who when he ſaw an alabaſter box of precious ointment poured on Chriſts head, he ſaid, <hi>To what purpoſe is this waſte? Mat.</hi> 26. 7, 8. And <hi>why was it not ſold, and given to the poore?</hi> but the Text takes notice, that he ſpake this, <hi>not that he cared for the poore, but becauſe he was a thiefe, Ioh.</hi> 12. 5, 6. ſo we have many that ſay, to what purpoſe is all this waſte? counting all loſt that is laid out for Chriſt and his cauſe: their friends or eſtates that are lent to Chriſt, they are all loſt. Is it poſſible to be a loſer in that ſervice, where the loſſe, if it may be ſo called, or rather the laying out, is a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117193:13"/> laying up, and the expence is the greateſt gaine. That man that breaks by his expences in this ſervice drives the moſt profitable trade, he breakes into treaſures and abundance: his few graines and drams and mites, are exchanged into pounds and talents. Doth Chriſt ſpeak paradoxes or falſhoods, when he ſpeaks of gaining by loſſes? <hi>Mark 8. 35. Whoſoever ſhall loſe his life for my ſake, ſhall ſave it.</hi> Doth not he drive a good trade, and is it not a very faire exchange that gets an hundred fold? and doth not he ſpeak true, that tells us this for a truth. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 29. whatever a man loſeth, he ſhall have an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold here in this life, beſides everlaſting life hereafter. Thus by a ſacred uſury men lay forth their poverty for treaſures, their nothing for all things. They are very ignorant that talk of loſſes in this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; they may be at coſt, they cannot be at a loſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there be a ſecond ſort of people to be reproved, who count that their chiefeſt gaine which is filched from God and his people and cauſe: among theſe I reckon thoſe that detaine unjuſtly the Miniſters dues <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>I am forty that we are fallen into thoſe times, in which men, under a pretence of Antichriſtianiſm, do detaine Church dues, though theſe were before ever the head or hornes of the beaſt did appeare ſo as to be taken notice of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeaks of Church rents, <hi>Hom.</hi> 31. in <hi>Matth.</hi> and <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bius</hi> of a houſe belonging to the Church, which he complaines was taken away by <hi>Paulus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſatenus, liv. 7. c.</hi> 24, then you have the edicts of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius Imp.</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſob. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 5. It was the care and piety in ancient times to give and ſo firmly to entail an allowance liberall to the miniſtry, as that the injury of the times ſhould no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> change and alter the property ſo farre as was poſſible, <hi>Synod. Rom. ſub Symmac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o Anno 503. tota contra invaſores Eccleſ. Concil. Meldenſ. c. 5. Concil. Gangrenſ. c. 8. Aurelean. Conc. 4. An. 543. c. 19.</hi> the words of the Synod 3. <hi>ſub Symmcaho in exemplari con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituti de Eccleſiae conſervandis,</hi> are very full to this purpoſe. <hi>Ne unquam praedium &amp;c. quocunq, titulo atq, commento alienentur. Si quis vero aliquid eorum alienare voluerit inef ſicax atq, irritum judicetur, ſitque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acienti, vel conſentienti, acci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ientiq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, anathema.</hi> If theſe were times of ignorance, God grant they do not condemne our ſeeing times, <hi>Vid, Sir Hen. Spelman d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>temerandis Eccleſtis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>. Theſe be farre from <hi>Davids</hi> temper, who would have thought himſelfe the poorer rather, if he had not laid out his riches on the work of God. Many there be, that make it their buſineſſe to keep back whatever they can from Chriſt; but let them be afraid of this by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> who were both ſmitten with ſudden death for their keeping back and lying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 2. 5. 10. How many are there that have builded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the ruines of the Church, and raiſed up their families upon that coſt that others have beſtowed on the Miniſtry and Saints. But all ſuch gaines will prove like the gold of Tholouſe, or the <hi>equus Sejanus,</hi> that never thrived in any hand; or like the coale ſtollen from the Altar by the Eagle, which when it was brought to her neſt, ſet it on fire; There goes a privy curſe, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117193:13"/> there is a ſecret hidden worme at the root, that will eat out all ſuch mens encreaſe. It is a deſign that carries much of hell in it, to make a poore, and ſo by that meanes you ſhall be ſure to have a baſe, illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate flattering Clergy. We read in ſtory, of two great perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſ. l. 7. c. 3. Niceph. l. 7. c. 3. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>codor. l. 3. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Niceph. l. 10. c.</hi> 5.</note> of the Church; the one under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> the other under <hi>Iulian.</hi> The former intended to root out all Profeſſours, <hi>&amp; occidit omnes Preſbyteros,</hi> he killed the Preachers; but for all this, Religion (as if it had been manured only) ſprang up the more and flouriſhed. But the other, <hi>occidit Preſbyterium,</hi> murthered the Presbytery; for he took away all the meanes that was allotted to maintaine the Preachers of the Goſpel; and this was the moſt deſperate perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are to be reproved, who are contented to be at ſome coſt for God, but not at much: ſome that have been at coſt in ſome kinde, in ſome part of their ſubſtance; but the coſt of their hearts, the travell of their braines, the deſires of their ſoules are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on the building of <hi>Babel:</hi> they lend a hand unwillingly to the one, but a heart moſt willingly to the other: they lend a ſhekel to the one, and give a talent to the other; they thus make friends of unrighteous Mammon, but when they faile, they ſhall never be received into everlaſting habitations: they give full weight, heapt up and preſt down to the one, but a gomer or an Ephah ſhall ſerve the turne for the other. Some there be that offer their ſervice, but it is as thoſe did <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 1, 2. and they will help to build the Lords houſe, but it is only that they might hinder the work, and deſtroy the building. I could wiſh that as thoſe were refuſed by <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Ieſhuah,</hi> and the chiefe of the Fathers, who told them, they had nothing to do with them to build an houſe unto their God, but they themſelves would build an houſe unto the Lord God of Iſrael, verſ. 3. that ſuch as theſe (and we have abundance of them) had never been entertained in the Lords work and ſervice.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, there be ſome that are at coſt, but it is rather for the building themſelves a name, then the Lord a houſe. They are at coſt, but it is as men that lay out their money for a purchaſe; they drive a bargaine for themſelves: they ſeeme to be very zealous, and they will tell you ſo, as <hi>Iehu</hi> did, and ſay, <hi>Come ſee my zeale for the Lord:</hi> If you did not ſee it, the Lord ſhould have no more from them, then he ſhould have had from the Phariſees, if a trumpet had not been ſounded before them, <hi>that they might have glory of men,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117193:14"/> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 2. they have ſo interwoven their own intereſts with Gods Cauſe, that as they have handled the matter, it looks like a linſey woolſey ſtuffe, and they have twiſted them ſo faſt and ſo cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that now it will be a very hard matter to ſever between them.</p>
            <p>5. There be that offer to God their own, but not that which God will own, even baſtards of their own begetting, and God muſt father them, that which beares their own image and ſuperſcription, and not Chriſts; they ſtamp inſtitutions of their own and baptize them in the name of Chriſt; they bring models ſpan out of their own brain for the moſt part, like a Spiders cobweb woven out of its own bowels, and theſe (as Spiders <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe) they will hang upon the Lords houſe, as the richeſt ornament they can beſtow. Look on the whole frame and modell of the Papacie, and ſee if from the Pope with his long, &amp;c. of Church-officers, down to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Apparitor, it be not a humane creation, there be ſome of whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay no more, but onely I think are too bold in this, that they entitle Chriſt to coyne <note place="margin">It was truly ſaid by the great Philoſopher, <hi>Multafa ſamul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s veris proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biltora a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>parent</hi> But as the great Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our ſayes, ſo ſay I in this caſe, <hi>Vt pule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er rimum judicem eſſe ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> videre. ſic proveris ſalſa probare turpiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt.</hi>
               </note> fetcht out of their own mint, but Chriſt will never own creations and productions of mens brains, nor will he accept of any coyn that is offered to him in the building of his houſe, but that which bears his own image: you know that counterfeit coyne though it beareas a ſimilitude with the true, yet it carries treaſon in the very forehead of it: You have ſeverall ſects walking in ſeverall ways, ſpeaking ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall languages, all helping to build, they ſay, the Lords Houſe; but if a man may judge by the confuſion of tongues, it is a <hi>Babel;</hi> however thoſe frames of mens ſetting up, and thoſe models of their creating, may ſeem to be very like the Lords, yet men ſhould not be ſo bold as to mak any like his, as it was ſaid concerning the anointing oyle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 31, 32. and when they have made it like his, put it off in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud me conſtat multos pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum potic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe ad detegendam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, niſi ſe illam penitus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripuiſſe credidiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Pet. Gaſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in praeſ. in 1 lib. exercit para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. adverſus Ariſtoleos. b Petr. Gaſſendus Exercit. 4. contr. Ariſt, aſſerit maximam eſſe incerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudmem doctrinae Exerc. 5. aſſerit &amp; probat quod in numera deficiant. 6. quòd in numera ſuperfluant. 7. quòd in numera ſallant. 8. quòd in numera a contradicant apud Ariſtotelem.</hi>
               </note> his name; this is to offer a great indignity to Chriſt. a I think that many had come neerer the truth in matters of the Church, if they had not thought ſo ſtiffely, and peremptorily affirmed, that they had found it; every one inſiſts upon his own <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and thinks every one out of the right way that is not in his: I may ſay of theſe as a very b learned Author doth concerning <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that many things are uncertain, many defective, many ſuperfluous, and many
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117193:14"/> falſe, and many contradictions, and therefore I conclude them not fit to be offered to the Lord. You have in <hi>Lucian</hi> and <hi>Boetius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Sophia</hi> brought in miſerably co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaining of the unworthy uſage of the pſeudo-Philoſophers, who did uſually put their falſities under her name, and canonize their errours under the name of truth: Sure I am, Chriſt hath as great reaſon to complain of ſome, who when their errours are purſued, fly to him as to a City of refuge, and ſhroud falſhood under the wing of truth. It is come to that paſſe <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iactabant qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſolaeciſmos eſſe laudes &amp; gemmas Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum;</hi> if you finde fault with their <hi>Haeccietates, &amp; aliquitates,</hi> and their abſurd incongruities, they anſwer you with laughter thus, <hi>Non curamus de verbibus, ſed de ſenſis. vide copioſe de his Hermol. Barb. Scalig. Exercit. Patricum Ariſtotelomast. tet. Gaſſendum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> now as it was in Philoſophy, that ſoleciſmes and barbariſmes in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſts Church, are accounted exquiſite and abſolute pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns to be commended unto others: I forbeare to quote ſome bloody tenets and licentious doctrines, all offered to Chriſt as his own inſtitutions; what they ſpeak and write, is as if it were <hi>è tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pode,</hi> you muſt not queſtion it, and as if there were an infallible <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> upon what they deliver for truth, it hath a paſport among many, and travels up and down without queſtion or controule: Such alſo is the frenzie of many, that as one ſpeakes concerning the <note n="d" place="margin">It was the ſaying of a profeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur of Philoſophy, <hi>mallet ſe errare cum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotele, quam bene ſentire cum aliis.</hi>
               </note> great Philoſopher, they had rather erre with their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Lords of their faith, then ſpeake truth with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>2. I come now to a uſe of Examination and enquiry into three <note place="margin">The ſecond uſe is, of Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after 3. particulars.</note> things: 1. What coſt we have been at for ſinne: 2. What coſt we have been at for God and his ſervice in generall. And 3. what coſt we have been at with the Cauſe of Chriſt now at this time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us call our ſelves to ſome account concerning our accounts <note place="margin">1. The firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry is to know what we have ſpent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſinnes, what coſt we have been at againſt God.</note> and expences in and upon ſinfull courſes, that ſo we may be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before the Lord this day. I feare that Tekel may be written upon what we have done for God, which was one of the words of the hand-writing that appeared on the wall, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 27. I feare that we being weighed ſhall be found too light; but our ſervice for ſinne hath been in a full meaſure, preſſed down, and heaped up, and running over. Let us conſider of all the yeeres that we have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, what have we laid out for God, what expence of time have we been at for him: Have we given him the tyth: I would we had.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117193:15"/> If our time were weighed in the ballances, we ſhall finde that wee have been at coſt but with minuts for God, and hours for ſin, at hours for God, and dayes for ſinne; at dayes for God, and weeks and months for ſinne; at weeks and months for God and whole yeers for ſinne; at ſome ſpare time for God, <hi>horae ſubſicivae</hi> muſt ſerve him, and at apprentiſhips with ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look at your coſt of ſtrength and paines, on whom have we beſtowed the firſt fruits of our ſtrength, the creame and flower of our ſelves and faculties, when we did run freſh and quick like veſſels newly ſet on broach, who did we draw forth our ſelves to then? the diſeaſes and aches in your limbs and bones will tell you that you doe poſſeſſe the ſinnes of your youth. <hi>Job</hi> 13. 26. ſo that we had need make that prayer with <hi>David, Pſal. 25. 7. Remember not the ſinnes of my youth;</hi> we may put in, nor of our riper age, in regard the ſtrength, and vigour, and activity both of the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have been given to ſinne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Look into your bills of accounts, and into your idle expences, and ſee who hath had moſt of your eſtate, of that kind of coſt: <note place="margin">Aurca hamo piſcantur, qui magno ſum, tu aut periculo, de rebus patvis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icent.</note> Conſider and be aſhamed, have you not been at a great deale of charges about things of no value, and even fiſh with a golden hook (as <hi>Auguſt. C.</hi> ſaid) for things of no price. Conſider, have none of you maintained more bruites meerly for pleaſure, than you have members of Jeſus Chriſt. I feare ſome of your ſinnes have been very coſtly. In the great book of accounts which the juſt Judge keeps by him, you may perhaps finde pride bringing in her bill with a prodigious <hi>Item</hi> of ſo many hundreds or thouſands it may be upon her ſcore: Then you may find luxury, and riot, and exceſſe come in with <hi>items</hi> of ſo many Lordſhips exhauſted for us; ſo many rents of thoſe and thoſe farmes and freeholds ſpent on us. Then come in Hawkes and Dogges, and horſes, with a black crew more embruitiſhed then the beaſts they look to, theſe bring in ſo many tenents rack-rents, and ſo many tenants ruines for us. Then covetouſneſſe and oppreſſion, &amp;c. they bring in their bills and <hi>items</hi> written in blood. <hi>Item,</hi> ſo many skins ſtayed off the backs of the poore, to cloath their Landlords. <hi>Item,</hi> ſo much fleſh off their backs to feed them. <hi>Item,</hi> ſo much blood drawn from them, to furniſh their great Lords with drink: Such a complaint in the like language was made againſt the heads of <hi>Iacob</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael, Micah</hi> 3. 2, 3. Then you have playes, and gaming and heatheniſh
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117193:15"/> ſports come in with vaſt Items, and great ſummes ſquandred away upon them; beſides the curſed lyes and oathes which come in as ſupernumerary to the account. I muſt not forget one that wipes her mouth, and ſaith I have done no ill. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 20. ſhe brings in as coſtly Items as any: She hath an Item for ſo much in ſattins and tiſſues taken up at ſuch a time for ſuites of apparell. Item, ſo much in an entertainment at a banquet, ſo much in Pearles and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amonds, and Jewels to adorn me <note n="a" place="margin">Doe but ſee what a cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties theſe kind of women car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with them, and thoſe very coſtly ones to, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note>. The Phyſitians and Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they bring in their bills, with an Item of ſo much for curing ſuch a diſeaſe, procured by a ſurfeit of drinking, and intemperate dyet and by other wayes which I leave to thoſe that heale them to tell of them. Then comes in the flattering trencher Chaplain, that flatters his Lord and Maſter in all theſe ſinfull expences, and dares not open his mouth againſt them, he brings in a bill much like the rate of <hi>Micahs</hi> Levite, <hi>Iud.</hi> 17. 10. ten ſhekels of ſilver a yeare, a ſuit of apparell, and victualls: But you will ſay, this is to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt expences for God; no, by no meanes, for this is not ſo much as the hire of a whore, which was not to be given to God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 18. It is a baſe contemptible ſumme that the Levite brings in, but it is too much for him that could ſee his Lord ſpend ſo much ſinfully, and not tell him of his abominations.</p>
            <q>Ah pudet haec dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</q>
            <p>I feare the Lord is now reckoning with our Kingdome, for theſe and the like expences and will proceed to take a very ſtrict account for the hundreds, the thouſands, and ten thouſands, and millions that have been ſpent, and ſpilt, and caſt away upon our ſinnes. Our ſins have been coſtly, and now they be bloody ſinnes. We have not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſinne with that which coſts us nought. The very ſuperfluity of <hi>England,</hi> and the expence of the ſecond and third courſes would have maintained another Kingdome: Nay, perhaps they might have gone neere to have maintained the whole family of Chriſt (I ſpeak of the true members) here below; for nature is contented with little, and grace with leſſe.</p>
            <p>I feare we have been at more coſt to purchaſe vengeance and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, hell and confuſion, then we might have been at for peace and the Goſpel, heaven and happineſſe. <hi>Demoſthones,</hi> though nor for conſcience, yet for coſt ſake would not lye with that famous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117193:16"/> Strumpet of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he ſaid he would not purchaſe repentance at ſo deare a rate I could have wiſhed we had not been at ſo much coſt to purchaſe ſo much miſery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us take a view of our coſt, for God and Chriſt: We would all of us be counted the ſervants of God, and heaven is in our deſires, if it be not in our earneſt endeavours; all of us would have the crown of righteouſneſſe, but all will nor goe to the price of it; they are loath to fight for it, and to finiſh their courſe, and to keep the faith which muſt goe before the crown, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. 8. We would all have the penny, but wee care not for working in the Vineyard, and bearing the burthen and heat of the day: Wee would all have the reward at the end, but we care not for running the race; we would all enter into glory, but we doe not like this ſtriving to enter: men therefore, beat their bargain as low as they can, and faine they would bring down the price of heaven, they are not good cuſtomers, they undervalue the commondity, they ſeeme to bid faire many of them, and <hi>Agrippa</hi>-like are almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded; but ſince they will not come off roundly with the Merchant, and ſell all that they have for Chriſt, but come neare the price, and not come up to it, and almoſt reach it, but not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they ſhall altogether goe without it: Such as theſe, bee like thoſe fordid Jewes, that valued Chriſt at the rate of a ſlave, as it is ſaid, <hi>Zech. 11. 13. a goodly price, I was prized at of them,</hi> &amp;c. Men will bee contented to be at coſt for any thing for vanity, that they may have it in poſſeſſion, rather then for glory, which they look on in reverſion, but are much miſtaken in the thing.</p>
            <p>Now when all coſts and charges are to be caſt up, and all accounts to be brought in at the laſt day, then will Chriſt bring in his arreares, and he will then tell how we would not bee at coſt for him; they will have a ſad reckoning, to whom Chriſt will ſay at the laſt day, as he is brought in ſpeaking, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 42. 43. You indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to love me, but when <hi>I was an hungred, yee gave me no meat,</hi> you would not be at the coſt of a piece of bread with mee; when <hi>I was thirſty, you gave me no drink,</hi> you would not be at the coſt of a draught of drink with me; <hi>I was a ſtranger, and yee took me not in,</hi> you could not afford me a little roome, or lodging in your houſe; <hi>I was naked, and yee clothed me not,</hi> you would not be at ſo much coſt as beſtow caſt clothes upon me: <hi>ſick, and in priſon, and yee viſited me not?</hi> When by reaſon of ill dyet, and hard and cruell uſage inpriſon,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117193:16"/> I was ready to be ſtarved, you would not ſo much as provide ſome comfortable thing for me, that might have refreſht me: How ſhall I ſay that you loved mee, when you ſuffred mee to beg and ſtarve, and goe naked, when a little coſt, only your ſuperfluities would have ſupported and maintained me in good faſhion. Then for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpel, he will bring his accounts in for that, he will then ſhew how that men like the fooliſh Virgins did procure lamps, and would be at the paines to trimme them perhaps, and likewiſe, to goe forth to meet the Bridegroom, but they would never bee at coſt for Oyle, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 12. Then for the confeſſing of Chriſt, hee he will bring in his charge upon that, and ſhew how men indeed, did take upon them to confeſſe him in ſhew, but they never would be at the coſt and paines to do it in truth. For they could hear his name blaſphemed, and torne in pieces by dogs, and never ſtand up in the vindication of his honour; they could ſee his ordinances tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled on, and not ſo much as afford a word or deed to advance them: So that Chriſt will ſay, thy confeſſion of me was a meere deniall of me, then ſhall they finde the truth of that, <hi>Mat. 10. 33. Whoſoever ſhall deny mee before men, him will I deny before my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then you ſhall have all holy duties and graces, bring in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and tell how they were performed and embraced: prayer will ſay, theſe Chriſtians did ſay a prayer, but never pray a prayer, they never ſighed or gronaed in prayer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. The word of God will ſpeak and ſay, that indeed they did hear it ſometime, but heeded it not, like thoſe in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33. 32. they heard, but did not practice; they read ſometime, but remembred not: Sabbaths will ſay, they never were entertained with delight, they never were ſanctified with ſpirituall rejoycing, they never obſerved them with any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, but ſpake their own words, thought their own thoughts, did their own works expreſſely contrary to that, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 58. 13. Then will Faſts come in and ſay, that they never afflicted their ſoules nor ſhed a teare in a whole day; nay, they have found their own pleaſure upon a faſting day, which the Lord complaines of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 3. All duties and graces will come in and ſay, that they never had the heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt, the ſoule was never engaged for them; ſo that all theſe that are in ſuch a condition, will bee looked upon as thoſe that offered that to God which coſt them nought, even as thoſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1. 8. that thought any thing good enough for God, even the halt, and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117193:17"/> blind, and the ſick. If heaven might be had with eaſe and idleneſſe, ſleep and ſecurity, careleſſeneſſe and negligence, and with <hi>Balaams</hi> wiſh, theſe will offer as faire as any, and there will be cuſtomers enough; indeed who would be out of it, of the vileſt of men, and what Saint would ever come there. Let us not flatter and deceive our ſelves; what ever we give to God muſt be ſuperlative and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; the choyſeſt ingredients are to bee put into every ſervice; he will have our righteouſneſſe an exceeding righteouſneſſe, <hi>Matt. 5. 20. Except your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, yee ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> What a ſhame will it be that pride and malice, and luxury, &amp;c. ſhall be able to bring in upon their accounts ſuch vaſt ſummes; and duties and graces, they bring in cyphers; or which is worſe, inſtead of accounts they will bring in complaints, and tell how they were vilified, and ſcorned, and trampled under feet: prayer and hearing the word, and reading, and holy meditation, &amp;c. will tell how they were not heeded, and how indeed <hi>Gallio</hi>-like they cared not for any of theſe things: they will tell how ſometimes they were put off, as <hi>Felix</hi> did <hi>Paul,</hi> to a more convenient ſeaſon: ſometimes, they were almoſt perſwaded like <hi>Agrippa;</hi> ſometimes, as <hi>Herod</hi> and his men of warre entertained Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. 11. they were ſet at nought, and mocked: ſometime the dancing of an <hi>Herodias,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the kiſſe of a <hi>Dalilah,</hi> ſometimes mammon, and the cares of the world, ſometimes gameſters, ſometimes good fellowes, ſometime one, ſometimes another interpoſed, that theſe duties and the reſt could finde no roome, no time could be ſpared for them; this will be but a ſad reckning: Think not that heaven will ſtoope to ſuch baſe offers as lazie, and negligent men doe make, for we ſee that we muſt eat our daily bread in the ſweat of our browes; much more the bread of life: We muſt ſweat for Chriſt, we muſt bleed, nay, we muſt die for him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider the Cauſe of God amongſt us, the building of the Lords houſe, the ſetting up of his ordinances, worſhip ſervice, and diſcipline amongſt us; what hath this buſineſſe coſt us? You will tell me, it hath coſt millions already; and yet I feare it hath coſt but little Let us caſt up the expences: at firſt it coſt you your plate, and ſuch like ſuperfluities, ſuch things as might be well ſpared: but may it not be ſaid of this offering, as Chriſt ſaid of theirs whom he ſaw caſt ſomething into the Treaſury, that <hi>you gave of your abundance:</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:117193:17"/> he looked on all that they caſt in as a thing of no value, not ſo much as a mite. But you will ſay, that there hath been a great deale offered ſince: I could wiſh we could ſay, it has been offered; hath it not been fetched and extorted from many as ſo many drops of blood? I am ſorry that ſuch is the hardneſſe of mens hearts, that our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be faine to make Ordinances to take that from men, which they will not offer, and that Gods Cauſe muſt be beholding to an Exciſe. I am ſorry that we ſhould be ſo little affected with the Cauſe amongſt us, that of neceſſity, by reaſon of the ſordid condition of men, Ordinances for loan, and that upon Intereſt, muſt be made to maintaine and ſupport it; whereas every one ſhould rate himſelfe, and ſtrive to goe before another in this buſineſſe; and put an exciſe upon himſelfe, not of a part but of all, not of his eſtate but his life in this buſineſſe. Is this to offer that to God, which coſts me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or rather is it not a kinde of expoſing to ſale, a bargaining, at leaſt with hopes of gaine. What a ſtrange thing is it, that the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith of the Kingdom ſhould go further then the publique faith of heaven? and that the Parliaments word ſhould be taken before Gods word? and that their ſecurity ſhould be thought better then the ſecurity of the bleſſed Trinity? God hath ſaid enough to us, if we would beleeve him, that we ſhall be no loſers by offering, by giving to his building, to his cauſe. Beſides, if we conſider the grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, murmuring, repining, the reluctance that goes along with it, which I cannot ſay, is given by men, but rather forced from them, certainly we muſt conclude, that <hi>Davids</hi> minde was wanting in this buſineſſe very much. The Scripture obſerves the wonderfull willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and readineſſe of thoſe that did help forward the work of the Sanctuary; there needed no rateing of them according to their eſtates, but every man offered ſo freely, that there was a reſtraint laid upon them, that they ſhould bring in no more. It ſeems alſo that at the building of the Temple, there was ſome unkinde and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotherly carriage of the chiefe among the Jews towards their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which did cauſe ſome griefe and trouble among them, <hi>Neh.</hi> 5. there were great complaints of exactions, ver. 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. which made ſome interruptions among them; but obſerve how <hi>Nehemiah</hi> behaved him elſe when he knew of it, verſ. 6, 7. he preſently recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the thing; whence I inferre, that it is the deſire of the Lord, that his work ſhould be carried on with all chearfulneſſe and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of minde, that whatever ſervice was to be offered to him,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117193:18"/> ſhould be a free will offering. Shall it ever be ſaid, that Chriſt hath a Cauſe in <hi>England</hi> to maintain, that cries for help, and offerings, for hearts and hands for ſubſtance, and lifes, and could not have them, at leaſt not willingly? Shall it ever be ſaid, that any of you have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom. Lanſius orat. cont. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaniam taurum eſt deus Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</hi>
               </note> a penny left that might advance this building, and you would not offer it. Then will I ſay, as the poore Indians (ſeeing the unſatiable deſire of the Spaniards after gold) ſaid, gold was the God of the Chriſtians; money is their god that will not give God their money. Shall it bee ſaid, that any of us have a hand, or a foot, or a limbe, or a life to loſe in this Cauſe, and wee would not ſpare them? We would not be at ſo much coſt in the buſineſſe, the time is now come, perhaps, that you may be put to it, as the young man in the Goſpel was, to ſell all, not to purchaſe, but to offer to Chriſt: It may be the time is come in, which Chriſt will call for honours and dignities; and will your Lordſhips carry them, and lay them at his feet; and ſay, theſe I lay down at thy foot-ſtoole, that thou mayeſt by them be advanced into thy Throne? Can you ſay, not my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Lord, but my life; honour me ſo far, as that I may looſe that for thy ſake, that haſt honoured me ſo far as to looſe thine for me: I am ſorry I have but one to looſe for thee, but if I had as many as there be ſands on the ſea, thou ſhouldeſt have them all. It may be the time is come, that he will call for all your rents, revenewes, poſſeſſions; and can you ſay, I am ſorry there is no more for my deare Saviour?</p>
            <p>Curſed be that honour and dignity, and let ignomy and reproach for ever light upon it, that ſhall refuſe to bee offred to the Lord: Curſed be that eſtate, and let beggery and baſeneſſe, ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, be in the habitations of thoſe that will not part their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for Chriſt: Curſed be thoſe limbs, and let them rot: And curſed bee thoſe lifes, and let them periſh that deny to offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Chriſt. He that thus loves not the Lord Chriſt, let him be <hi>Anathema, Maranatha, 1 Cor.</hi> 16. 22. And he loves him not, Chriſt himſelfe being interpreter, that will not lay down his life for him. I hope none that heares me are thus curſed, but thoſe that will not now offer their help to the Lord againſt the mighty, they are like <hi>Meroz,</hi> curſed, and curſed bitterly to.</p>
            <p>However we thus ſpeak to you in the name of God, yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that God doth not ſtand in need of any thing you have, but he is pleaſed to put you upon the tryall; hee will ſee what you will doe for him: He needs not aske your leave, hee may take what hee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117193:18"/> pleaſeth from you, as having a greater intereſt and propriety in what you poſſeſſe, then you have your ſelves; he is pleaſed to take what you give freely, and to call it a gift, but if you ſtand upon it, hee will let you know that it was his, before it was yours, and now it is yours, yet it is more his then yours: Heare what God ſayes, <hi>Pſal. 50. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. All the beaſts of the forreſt bee mine, and the cattell upon a thouſand hils,</hi> &amp;c. but ver. 14. he tells you what he looks for, <hi>Offer unto God thanksgiving, and pay thy vowes unto the moſt High:</hi> he looks for offering, though he ſtands in need of none. And <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, that he was ready to offer ſacrifice, if God would accept it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 16. but verſ. 17. he tells what ſacrifice God did delight in. This is a day of Humiliation, and this is the moſt proper offering for the day; which ſhould be a heart-breaking day; he that offers to God a faſt without afflicting of his ſoule, without being in bitterneſſe for his ſinnes, without mourning, without ſighs and groanes, without teares, or trouble, that hath dry eyes, without ſome pangs and travell of ſoule, without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict of and agony in his ſpirit, without ſome kind of bleeding in his heart, he offers a ſacrifice that coſts him nought; the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſuch a faſt as this, as hee did theirs, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 58. 5. but the coſtly faſt that God looks at, is verſ. 6. 7. That is a coſtly faſt indeed, when heaven and Earth are at ſtrife and contention; when you ſtrive to offer to God rivers of teares, then doth God even ſtrive to offer to you rivers of conſolations: when you are at coſt with God in your hearts, he is at coſt with you in his bleſſings. The Lord even ſpeakes this language to you to day, thoſe ſinnes that have coſt you thouſands to maintaine them, let them now coſt you ſome teares from hearts truly penitent, and deeply affected with the ſenſe of them, and all your ſinnes ſhall be pardoned, and my debt book ſhall be croſſed, all your iniquities ſhall be blotted out, I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them no more.</p>
            <p>Here we come to offer to God a ſervice of his own preſcribing; but if we doe not offer according to his own way, we ſhall not onely, not be accepted of God, but we ſhall have that which wee never looked for from God: he will not onely refuſe the ſervice which we offer, but he will ſend ſomething that we would not willingly have, <hi>Ier. 14. 12. When they faſt, I will not heare their cry, and when they offer burnt offrings, and an oblation, I will not accept them:</hi> This one would think were bad enough, to looſe their labour, but that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117193:19"/> ſhall not ſatisfie; for it followes, <hi>but I will conſume them,</hi> &amp;c. That man that comes to God in his ſinnes, on a faſting day, he is refuſed with contempt, with an <hi>who hath required this at your hand,</hi> Iſa. 1. 12. and with a ſcornfull objurgation, <hi>What haſt thou to doe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Statutes, or take my Covenant into thy mouth? Seeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my word behind thee,</hi> Pſal. 50. 16. 17.</p>
            <p>Conſider further, that when ever we appeare before the Lord in our ſins, we doe but like thoſe that are in debt, when they come into their creditors ſight, they put them in minde of that which they owe them, and by that meanes they are moved to clap a ſerjeant on there backs. Every one of us, is in great arreares with God, much in debt, and have we procured a pardon? Remember that you are in great danger, if you have not, for it is ſaid, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8. 13. Then even then, when they are ſacrificing, <hi>Then will I remember their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and viſit their ſinnes:</hi> juſt then, when they think to pleaſe God, then will God remember them in fury.</p>
            <p>Our ſinnes have coſt us very deare already; let us reſolve never to be at more coſt with them, unleſſe as Sates are with malefactours to correct, puniſh, condemne, and execute them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die veneris 29. November. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is this day Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, That this Houſe doth hereby returne thanks to Mr</hi> Henry Wilkinſon, <hi>for his great Paines taken in his Sermon preached by him on Wedneſday laſt before their Lordſhips in the Abby Church</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>it being the day of the Monthly Faſt: And this Houſe doth hereby deſire him to Print and Publiſh the ſame. And laſtly, it is Orderd that none ſhall print or reprint his ſaid Sermon without being authorized ſo to doe under the hand of the ſaid Mr</hi> Wilkinſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jo. Brown, Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint CHR. MEREDITH, and SA. GELLIBRAND, to Print this Sermon,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Wilkinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
